If animals eat other animals, do you think that nature is violent and immoral?
When we look at how we should live as
humans that have the ability to
choose to live in very different ways
than we lived ancestrally,
sometimes we look to nature for models
and its important to understand which models
are relevant in which ones aren't
relevant.
And so in the animal kingdom we see
predatory cycles, we see predation and
some animals eating plants and some
animals eating other animals
and we see that's actually part the balance of the whole system, that the animals
that are eating plants actually don't regulate their own consumption
and they don't regulate their own
reproduction so they would breed themselves
beyond the caring capacity of their
environment and the process of
prey checking them is actually what
creates a dynamic balance.
When many look at that they
say that survival of the fittest is what drives evolution
and it's part of what drives balance and
it's a part of nature and that we're part of the food chain
where animals, we're part of the biosphere and that we should embrace being part of that
and there's a couple distinctions that
are really key
I think to note here. One is
is a really subtle scientific
and philosophic point is
that the reason there's predation in
nature the reason as a predatory process
and it is violent and any
animal that is on the prey side of
the equation will acknowledge that really clearly,
is because the prey animals can't self-regulate sustainably because they don't have
the cognitive capacities, the
neurophysiological capacities to be able to
assess what the caring capacity of their
environment is
and then say hey we're gonna stop
reproducing now, we're going to slow
reproduction rates, we're going to slow our consumption rates to actually live sustainably.
So when they start to out-breed
their own
environmental capacities and there starts to be a scarcity resources for the
creatures, some of the creatures start
actually prey on each other because
there isn't enough of the base
materials anymore there's too many of
them they go into competition
as a function of that scarcity, as a
function of their inability,
to modulate their own sustainability and
then those ones
have an evolutionary niche were they
evolve in the direction of
predatory kind of animals.
So the predatory process
rises out of the unsustainability
or the incapacity of a species to be
self-sustaining, so that violence is
actually necessary
for miss the species to continue
and for the biosphere to continue and so
it's not like it's just a good thing
it's a necessary thing.
In nature it is a necessary thing.
With humans
there is the fascinating thing that evolution
drives more complexity, more complex
ability to respond so we see
from a reptilian nervous system that's
kind of
on/off modulated responses that
experience physiologic pain and pleasure
in those response capacities
to mammalian nervous systems and their ability for emotion
to neocortex primates and
dolphins purposes and their
capacity for cognition
to then with humans in the prefrontal
cortex and the capacity for abstraction.
We're the first creature that has this
abstraction capacity, we can actually
assess our environment's caring
capacity. We don't do a good job of this yet
but we could
assess hey how many of us can really
say here based on the resource per
capita needs.
And then we could modulate the
efficiency of how we consume
and actually modulate our own reproduction to stay with in those caring capacity limits
so that we didn't need
ongoing violence a check our numbers. Now, this is a capacity we have neurophysiologically
because of our prefrontal cortex and uniquely human capacities, but it's not one we've exercised
well yet. We're still
breeding irrespective of the the
resource limits on the planet and we're
still consuming irrespective of the
unsustainable resource limits of the planet and as a result some human start praying on
other humans
in different ways right through all
kinds a pathological competition.
It's an important note though that we
don't have to do this
and that we're actually at the point
right now where because of our data
harvesting capacities and really
our ability to assess planetarily
things that we couldn't even a few
generations ago
because our technological capacities, that we really are for the first time
capable of saying how many people can
the earth support sustainably in harmony with
the rest to the biosphere
and how do we consciously self-regulate
as a whole species
how we relate to the planet sustainably where there's
there's no need for predation
process continuing.
And what's so exciting about that to me is that we're the first species that really has the capacity
to end the need for violence and to
really step up to that capacity, such
an exciting thing.